<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Juan Díaz-Colunga</title>
    <link>https://jdiazc9.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdiazc9.github.io/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Juan Díaz-Colunga</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2024 Juan Díaz-Colunga</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 02:29:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdiazc9.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Juan Díaz-Colunga</title>
      <link>https://jdiazc9.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to my blog!</title>
      <link>https://jdiazc9.github.io/post/20200123_my-first-blog-entry/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 02:29:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdiazc9.github.io/post/20200123_my-first-blog-entry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./thisiswhere.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./ifihadone.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;but trust me, I am filled with good intentions and plan to update this blog periodically.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What this blog is (and isn&#39;t) going to be // Lo que va a ser (y no va a ser) este blog</title>
      <link>https://jdiazc9.github.io/post/20200123_what-is-this-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 02:29:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdiazc9.github.io/post/20200123_what-is-this-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Versión en español más abajo // Spanish version below)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🇺🇸🇬🇧&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early 2020 I committed to &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdiazc9.github.io/post/20200123_my-first-blog-entry/&#34;&gt;keeping this blog updated&lt;/a&gt;. More than four years and zero posts later, it’s time to fool myself again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, I think I figured out what I would like to do here. In late 2022 I moved back to Spain, and I have been working for the Spanish National Research Council (CSIC) ever since, first at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cnb.csic.es/index.php/en&#34;&gt;National Center for Biotechnology&lt;/a&gt; in Madrid and now at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ibfg.usal-csic.es/index-en.php&#34;&gt;Institute of Functional Biology and Genomics&lt;/a&gt; in Salamanca. CSIC is the largest research institution in Spain and one of the most relevant in Europe. Its core financial support comes from public funds allocated by the Spanish government, covering most of the funding for research projects in Spain and also, well, my own salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As scientists, we have a responsibility to promote social development. This includes generating fundamental knowledge and technological tools to address present and future global challenges. It also includes promoting equity and inclusion, social justice, and gender equality. Additionally (and this is the matter at hand), it involves ensuring free and democratized access to information and knowledge. All of these responsibilities, of course, are even more critical when science is publicly funded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s why I intend to turn this blog into a platform for disseminating the work we do in our lab. The goal is not to do &amp;ldquo;general&amp;rdquo; science communication: in Spain, there are already excellent science communicators for the general public, such as Sandra Ortonobes (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@Lahiperactina&#34;&gt;La Hiperactina&lt;/a&gt;), Rocío Vidal (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCoXtmmnLCbXDiSo8GxsmOzA&#34;&gt;La Gata de Schrödinger&lt;/a&gt;), Javier Santaolalla (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@dateunvlog&#34;&gt;Date un Vlog&lt;/a&gt;), or Eduardo Sáenz (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@Derivando&#34;&gt;Derivando&lt;/a&gt;), to name just a few examples (somewhat) related to my own research area(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is to explain the specific work of &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; group in simple terms, making it accessible to all kinds of audiences. I want to convey &lt;em&gt;why we do what we do&lt;/em&gt; in our lab, and why it is important that we do it. I will try to post here every time the lab produces something (say, every time we publish a scientific paper). I might also periodically provide summaries of other types of activities that we organize or participate in, such as talks, workshops, conferences, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contents will be in Spanish from now on. I believe that this is the best way to make them accessible to the largest number of readers among those who may be remotely interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome (back) to my blog!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🇪🇸&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A principios de 2020 me comprometí a &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdiazc9.github.io/post/20200123_my-first-blog-entry/&#34;&gt;actualizar este blog&lt;/a&gt; con regularidad. Más de cuatro años después, y sin haber posteado nada, ha llegado el momento de volver a engañarme a mí mismo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La cuestión es que creo que por fin he decidido el enfoque que quiero darle a este espacio. A finales de 2022 me mudé de vuelta a España, y desde entonces he estado trabajando para el Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas (CSIC), primero en el &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cnb.csic.es/index.php/en&#34;&gt;Centro Nacional de Biotecnología&lt;/a&gt; en Madrid y ahora en el &lt;a href=&#34;https://ibfg.usal-csic.es/index-en.php&#34;&gt;Instituto de Biología Funcional y Genómica&lt;/a&gt; en Salamanca. El CSIC es la mayor institución científica de España y una de las más importantes de Europa. El grueso de su financiación sale de fondos públicos adjudicados por el gobierno central, con los que se cubren la mayoría de proyectos de investigación y también, en fin, mi propio salario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Como científicos, tenemos la responsabilidad de promover el desarrollo social. Esto incluye la generación de conocimiento fundamental y de herramientas tecnológicas que permitan abordar los retos globales presentes y futuros. También incluye la promoción de la equidad e inclusión, de la justicia social, y de la igualdad de género. Además (y he aquí el tema que nos ocupa), implica velar por el acceso libre y democratizado a la información y el conocimiento. Todas estas responsabilidades, claro, se agudizan cuando la ciencia se financia con fondos públicos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por eso mi intención es convertir este blog en una plataforma de divulgación para el trabajo que llevamos a cabo en el laboratorio. El objetivo no es hacer divulgación científica “en general”: en España ya existen muy buenos divulgadores y divulgadoras orientados al público no especializado, como Sandra Ortonobes (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@Lahiperactina&#34;&gt;La Hiperactina&lt;/a&gt;), Rocío Vidal (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCoXtmmnLCbXDiSo8GxsmOzA&#34;&gt;La Gata de Schrödinger&lt;/a&gt;), Javier Santaolalla (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@dateunvlog&#34;&gt;Date un Vlog&lt;/a&gt;), o Eduardo Sáenz (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@Derivando&#34;&gt;Derivando&lt;/a&gt;), por poner sólo algunos ejemplos más o menos relacionados con mi(s) área(s) de investigación.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La idea es explicar el trabajo concreto de &lt;em&gt;nuestro&lt;/em&gt; grupo en términos simples, de forma que sea accesible a todo tipo de públicos. Mi intención es transmitir &lt;em&gt;por qué hacemos lo que hacemos&lt;/em&gt; en el laboratorio, y por qué es importante que lo hagamos. Intentaré publicar un post de este tipo cada vez que el laboratorio produzca algo (digamos, cada vez que publiquemos un artículo científico). Quizás también haga resúmenes periódicos de otro tipo de actividades que organicemos o en las que participemos, como charlas, talleres, congresos, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El contenido estará, a partir de ahora, en español. Entiendo que es la mejor manera de que sea accesible para el mayor número de lectores entre aquellos que puedan tener un mínimo interés en él.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bienvenid@s (otra vez) a mi blog!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
